<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38850497</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>08</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1572-8633</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>27</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medicine, health care, and philosophy</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Med Health Care Philos</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Patient autonomy in the era of the sustainability crisis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>399</StartPage><EndPage>405</EndPage><MedlinePgn>399-405</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11019-024-10214-x</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In the realm of medical ethics, the foundational principle of respecting patient autonomy holds significant importance, often emerging as a central concern in numerous ethically complex cases, as authorizing medical assistance in dying or healthy limb amputation on patient request. Even though advocates for either alternative regularly utilize prima facie principles to resolve ethical dilemmas, the interplay between these principles is often the core of the theoretical frameworks. As the ramifications of the sustainability crisis become increasingly evident, there is a growing need to integrate awareness for sustainability into medical decision-making, thus reintroducing potential conflict with patient autonomy. The contention of this study is that the ethical standards established in the 20th century may not adequately address the challenges that have arisen in the 21st century. The author suggests an advanced perception of patient autonomy that prioritizes fostering patients' knowledge, self-awareness, and sense of responsibility, going beyond a sole focus on their intrinsic values. Empowering patients could serve as a tool to align patient autonomy, beneficence, and the aim to reduce resource consumption.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kov&#xe1;cs</LastName><ForeName>Szil&#xe1;rd D&#xe1;vid</ForeName><Initials>SD</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1541-3177</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Behavioural Sciences, Semmelweis University, Budapest, 1089, Hungary. kovacs.szilard@phd.semmelweis.hu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Med Health Care Philos</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9815900</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1386-7423</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D026684" MajorTopicYN="Y">Personal Autonomy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003657" MajorTopicYN="Y">Decision Making</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000941" MajorTopicYN="N">ethics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004992" MajorTopicYN="N">Ethics, Medical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010686" MajorTopicYN="N">Philosophy, Medical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Climate change</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Green bioethics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Patient autonomy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Patient empowerment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sustainability</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The author has no financial or non-financial interests to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38850497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11310236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11019-024-10214-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11019-024-10214-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abbasi, Kamran, Parveen Ali, Virginia Barbour, Thomas Benfield, Kirsten Bibbins-Domingo, Gregory E. Erhabor, and Stephen Hancocks et al. 2023. Time to Treat the Climate and Nature Crisis as One Indivisible Global Health Emergency. The American Journal of Bioethics 23. Taylor &amp; Francis: 1&#x2013;4. 10.1080/15265161.2023.2276980.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aho, Brett. 2020. and Roberta Duffield. Beyond surveillance capitalism: Privacy, regulation and big data in Europe and China. Economy and Society 49. Routledge: 187&#x2013;212. 10.1080/03085147.2019.1690275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersen, Mads Peter, Ole John Sulbaek, Nielsen, and Jodi D. Sherman. 2023. Assessing the potential climate impact of anaesthetic gases. The Lancet Planetary Health 7. Elsevier: e622&#x2013;e629. 10.1016/S2542-5196(23)00084-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37438003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Auckland, Cressida, Jennifer Blumenthal-Barby, Kenneth Boyd, Brian D. Earp, Lucy Frith, Zo&#xeb; Fritz, John McMillan, Arianne Shahvisi, and Mehrunisha Suleman. 2022. Medical ethics and the climate change emergency. Journal of Medical Ethics 48 Institute of Medical Ethics 939&#x2013;940. 10.1136/jme-2022-108738.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36442972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aujoulat, Isabelle, and William d&#x2019;Hoore, Alain Deccache. 2007. Patient empowerment in theory and practice: polysemy or cacophony? Patient Education and Counseling 66: 13&#x2013;20. 10.1016/j.pec.2006.09.008. 10.1016/j.pec.2006.09.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pec.2006.09.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17084059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Batavia, Chelsea, Jeremy T. Bruskotter, and Julia A. Jones, Michael Paul Nelson. 2020. Exploring the ins and outs of biodiversity in the moral community. Biological Conservation 245: 108580. 10.1016/j.biocon.2020.108580.10.1016/j.biocon.2020.108580</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biocon.2020.108580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beauchamp, Tom L, and F Childress James. 2019. Principles of Biomedical Ethics. 8th edition. New York: Oxford University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bester, Johan Christiaan. 2020. Beneficence, Interests, and Wellbeing in Medicine: What It Means to Provide Benefit to Patients. The American Journal of Bioethics 20. Taylor &amp; Francis: 53&#x2013;62. 10.1080/15265161.2020.1714793.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32105204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cameron, Genevieve, Anya G&#xf6;pfert, and Tim Gardner. 2021. Going green: what do the public think about the NHS and climate change? - The Health Foundation. https://www.health.org.uk/publications/long-reads/going-green-what-do-the-public-think-about-the-nhs-and-climate-change. Accessed June 4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Stacy S., Sunit Das. 2022. What are my options? Physicians as ontological decision architects in surgical informed consent. Bioethics 36: 936&#x2013;939. 10.1111/bioe.13076. 10.1111/bioe.13076</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bioe.13076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35912521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen, Shlomo. 2019. The logic of the interaction between beneficence and respect for autonomy. Medicine Health Care and Philosophy 22: 297&#x2013;304. 10.1007/s11019-018-9876-4. 10.1007/s11019-018-9876-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11019-018-9876-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30467682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D&#x2019;Ancona, Grainne, Andrew Cumella, Charlotte Renwick, and Samantha Walker. 2021. The sustainability agenda and inhaled therapy: what do patients want? European Respiratory Journal 58. 10.1183/13993003.congress-2021.PA3399. European Respiratory Society.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dwyer, James. 2009. How to connect Bioethics and Environmental Ethics: Health, sustainability, and Justice. Bioethics 23: 497&#x2013;502. 10.1111/j.1467-8519.2009.01759.x. 10.1111/j.1467-8519.2009.01759.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1467-8519.2009.01759.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19788647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engelsma, Coos. 2023. Sharing a medical decision. Medicine Health Care and Philosophy. 10.1007/s11019-023-10179-3.10.1007/s11019-023-10179-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11019-023-10179-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10904442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38010578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felce, David, and Jonathan Perry. 1995. Quality of life: its definition and measurement. Research in Developmental Disabilities 16: 51&#x2013;74. 10.1016/0891-4222(94)00028-8. 10.1016/0891-4222(94)00028-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0891-4222(94)00028-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7701092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Going green: what do the public think about the NHS and climate change? - The Health Foundation. 2024. https://www.health.org.uk/publications/long-reads/going-green-what-do-the-public-think-about-the-nhs-and-climate-change. Accessed January 4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goodman, Colin, and Timothy Houk. 2022. Misapplying autonomy: why patient wishes cannot settle treatment decisions. Theoretical Medicine and Bioethics 43: 289&#x2013;305. 10.1007/s11017-022-09593-0. 10.1007/s11017-022-09593-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11017-022-09593-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36303064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greene, Jeremy, Caroline L. Skolnik, and Maria W. Merritt. 2022. How medicine becomes trash: disposability in health care. The Lancet 400. Elsevier: 1298&#x2013;1299. 10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01941-9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herlitz, Anders, Erik Malmqvist, and Christian Munthe. 2023. Green&#x2019; bioethics widens the scope of eligible values and overrides patient demand: comment on Parker. Journal of Medical Ethics 49 Institute of Medical Ethics 100&#x2013;101. 10.1136/jme-2022-108849.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36564173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horn, Ruth. 2020. The right to a self-determined death as expression of the right to freedom of personal development: the German Constitutional Court takes a clear stand on assisted suicide. Journal of Medical Ethics 46 Institute of Medical Ethics 416&#x2013;417. 10.1136/medethics-2020-106197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32220872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howorka, Kinga, Jiri Pumprla, Dorothea Wagner-Nosiska, Helga Grillmayr, Christoph Schlusche, and Alfred Schabmann. 2000. Empowering diabetes out-patients with structured education:: short-term and long-term effects of functional insulin treatment on perceived control over diabetes. Journal of Psychosomatic Research 48: 37&#x2013;44. 10.1016/S0022-3999(99)00074-4. 10.1016/S0022-3999(99)00074-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0022-3999(99)00074-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10750628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jennings, Bruce. 2009. Public Health and Liberty: beyond the Millian paradigm. Public Health Ethics 2: 123&#x2013;134. 10.1093/phe/php009.10.1093/phe/php009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/phe/php009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakuk, Peter. 2007. The slippery slope of the middle ground: reconsidering euthanasia in Britain. HEC Forum: An Interdisciplinary Journal on Hospitals&#x2019; Ethical and Legal Issues 19: 145&#x2013;159. 10.1007/s10730-007-9036-3. 10.1007/s10730-007-9036-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10730-007-9036-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17694995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katzenberger, Anja, Anders Levermann, Jacob Schewe, and Julia Pongratz. 2022. Intensification of Very Wet Monsoon Seasons in India Under Global Warming. Geophysical Research Letters 49: e10.1029/2022GL098856.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keizer, Ellen, Marleen Smits, Yvonne Peters, Linda Huibers, Paul Giesen, and Michel Wensing. 2015. Contacts with out-of-hours primary care for nonurgent problems: patients&#x2019; beliefs or deficiencies in healthcare? BMC Family Practice 16: 157. 10.1186/s12875-015-0376-9. 10.1186/s12875-015-0376-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12875-015-0376-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4625560</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26510620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirsch, Stuart. 2020. Why Pacific islanders stopped worrying about the Apocalypse and started fighting Climate Change. American Anthropologist 122: 827&#x2013;839. 10.1111/aman.13471.10.1111/aman.13471</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/aman.13471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitano, Taito, Bradley J Langford, Kevin A Brown, Andrea Pang, Branson Chen, Gary Garber, and Nick Daneman et al. 2021. The Association between High and Unnecessary Antibiotic Prescribing: a Cohort Study using Family Physician Electronic Medical records. Clinical Infectious Diseases 72: e345&#x2013;e351. 10.1093/cid/ciaa1139. 10.1093/cid/ciaa1139</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa1139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32785696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kovacs, Jozsef. 2009. Whose identity is it anyway? The American Journal of Bioethics: AJOB 9: 44&#x2013;45. 10.1080/15265160802617886.10.1080/15265160802617886</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15265160802617886</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19132622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kov&#xe1;cs, J&#xf3;zsef. 2006. A modern orvosi etika alapjai. vol. 2 Budapest: Medicina K&#xf6;nyvkiad&#xf3; Zrt.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kov&#xe1;cs, J&#xf3;zsef. 2008. K&#xf6;rnyezeti Etika. Vil&#xe1;goss&#xe1;g 49: 75&#x2013;107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lake, Robert W. 2017. Big Data, urban governance, and the ontological politics of hyperindividualism. Big Data &amp; Society 4. SAGE Publications Ltd: 2053951716682537. 10.1177/2053951716682537.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, Lisa M. 2017. A Bridge Back to the Future: Public Health Ethics, Bioethics, and Environmental Ethics. The American Journal of Bioethics 17. Taylor &amp; Francis: 5&#x2013;12. 10.1080/15265161.2017.1353164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28829266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenzen, Manfred, Arunima Malik, Mengyu Li, Jacob Fry, Helga Weisz, Peter-Paul Pichler, Leonardo Suveges Moreira Chaves, Anthony Capon, and and David Pencheon. 2020a. The environmental footprint of health care: a global assessment. The Lancet Planetary Health 4. Elsevier: e271&#x2013;e279. 10.1016/S2542-5196(20)30121-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32681898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenzen, Manfred, Arunima Malik, Mengyu Li, Jacob Fry, Helga Weisz, Peter-Paul Pichler, Leonardo Suveges Moreira Chaves, Anthony Capon, and David Pencheon. 2020b. The environmental footprint of health care: a global assessment. The Lancet Planetary Health 4: e271&#x2013;e279. 10.1016/S2542-5196(20)30121-2. 10.1016/S2542-5196(20)30121-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2542-5196(20)30121-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32681898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levy, Neil. 2014. Forced to be free? Increasing patient autonomy by constraining it. Journal of Medical Ethics 40 Institute of Medical Ethics 293&#x2013;300. 10.1136/medethics-2011-100207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3995287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22318413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liew, K. L., and A. Wilkinson. 2017. P280 How do we choose inhalers? patient and physician perspectives on environmental, financial and ease-of-use factors. Thorax 72. BMJ Publishing Group Ltd: A235&#x2013;A237. 10.1136/thoraxjnl-2017-210983.422.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, Jing, Xu Wan, and Bin Wu. 2020. The Cost-Effectiveness of Lifestyle Interventions for Preventing Diabetes in a Health Resource-Limited Setting. Journal of Diabetes Research 2020. Hindawi: e7410797. 10.1155/2020/7410797.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7174913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32352016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macpherson, Cheryl Cox. 2014. Climate change matters. Journal of Medical Ethics 40 Institute of Medical Ethics 288&#x2013;290. 10.1136/medethics-2012-101084.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23665996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mallinas, Stephanie R., K. Jon, Maner, and E. Ashby Plant. 2021. What factors underlie attitudes regarding protective mask use during the COVID-19 pandemic? Personality and Individual Differences 181: 111038. 10.1016/j.paid.2021.111038. 10.1016/j.paid.2021.111038</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.paid.2021.111038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8164375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34092834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merino, Sabrina, Mar&#xed;a E. Aruanno, and Ricardo J. Gelpi. 2017. and Ana M. Rancich. The prohibition of euthanasia and medical oaths of Hippocratic Stemma. Acta Bioethica 23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oreskes, Naomi. 2004. The Scientific Consensus on Climate Change. Science 306: 1686&#x2013;1686. American Association for the Advancement of Science10.1126/science.1103618. 10.1126/science.1103618</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1103618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15576594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parker, Joshua. 2023. Barriers to green inhaler prescribing: ethical issues in environmentally sustainable clinical practice. Journal of Medical Ethics 49 Institute of Medical Ethics 92&#x2013;98. 10.1136/jme-2022-108388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9887388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35981864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pichler, Peter-Paul, Ingram S. Jaccard, and Ulli Weisz. 2019. and Helga Weisz. International comparison of health care carbon footprints. Environmental Research Letters 14. IOP Publishing: 064004. 10.1088/1748-9326/ab19e1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pizza, Lizette, Deborah Kelemen. 2023. Are humans part of the Natural World? U.S. children&#x2019;s and adults&#x2019; Concept of Nature and its relationship to environmental concern. Topics in Cognitive Science 15: 452&#x2013;479. 10.1111/tops.12675. 10.1111/tops.12675</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/tops.12675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37352441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pullman, Daryl. 2023. Slowing the Slide Down the Slippery Slope of Medical Assistance in Dying: Mutual Learnings for Canada and the US. The American Journal of Bioethics 23. Taylor &amp; Francis: 64&#x2013;72. 10.1080/15265161.2023.2201190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37166283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Resnik, David B. 2023. and Jonathan Pugh. Green bioethics, patient autonomy and informed consent in healthcare. Journal of Medical Ethics. Institute of Medical Ethics. 10.1136/jme-2023-109404.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11014890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37833040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richie, Cristina. 2019. Principles of green bioethics: sustainability in health care. East Lansing: Michigan State University.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richie, Cristina. 2023a. Green informed consent in the classroom, clinic, and consultation room. Medicine Health Care and Philosophy 26: 507&#x2013;515. 10.1007/s11019-023-10163-x. 10.1007/s11019-023-10163-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11019-023-10163-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10725850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37584839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richie, Cristina. 2023b. Environmental sustainability and the paradox of prevention. Journal of Medical Ethics Institute of Medical Ethics. 10.1136/jme-2023-109437.10.1136/jme-2023-109437</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/jme-2023-109437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38124200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rieder, Travis N. 2023. Green prescribing is good, but patients do not have a duty to accept it. Journal of Medical Ethics 49 Institute of Medical Ethics 104&#x2013;105. 10.1136/jme-2022-108846.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36599665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rigby, Brieann, Xavier Symons. 2023. Abortion, euthanasia, and the limits of principlism. Medicine Health Care and Philosophy 26: 549&#x2013;556. 10.1007/s11019-023-10162-y. 10.1007/s11019-023-10162-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11019-023-10162-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37470922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rocque, Rhea J., Caroline Beaudoin, Ruth Ndjaboue, Laura Cameron, Louann Poirier-Bergeron, Rose-Alice Poulin-Rheault, Catherine Fallon, Andrea C. Tricco, and Holly O. Witteman. 2021. Health effects of climate change: an overview of systematic reviews. BMJ Open 11 British Medical Journal Publishing Group e046333. 10.1136/bmjopen-2020-046333.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8191619</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34108165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin, Michael A. 2014. The collaborative autonomy model of medical decision-making. Neurocritical Care 20: 311&#x2013;318. 10.1007/s12028-013-9922-2. 10.1007/s12028-013-9922-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12028-013-9922-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24233814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, Sharon Swee-Lin, Nadee Goonawardene. 2017. Internet Health Information seeking and the patient-physician relationship: a systematic review. Journal of Medical Internet Research 19: e5729. 10.2196/jmir.5729.10.2196/jmir.5729</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/jmir.5729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5290294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28104579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ten Have, Henk. 2020. and Bert Gordijn. Sustainability. Medicine, Health Care and Philosophy 23: 153&#x2013;154. 10.1007/s11019-020-09946-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32166436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ten Have, Henk, Bert Gordijn. 2023. Green bioethics. Medicine Health Care and Philosophy 26: 497&#x2013;498. 10.1007/s11019-023-10182-8. 10.1007/s11019-023-10182-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11019-023-10182-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37855994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thiel, Cassandra, Cristina Richie. 2022. Carbon emissions from Overuse of U.S. Health Care: medical and ethical problems. Hastings Center Report 52: 10&#x2013;16. 10.1002/hast.1404.10.1002/hast.1404</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hast.1404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35993105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNESCO. 2005. Records of the General Conference, 33rd session, Paris, 3-21 October 2005, v. 1: Resolutions - UNESCO Digital Library.&#xa0;https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000142825.page=80. Accessed June 4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Universal Declaration on Bioethics and Human Rights - Legal Affairs. 2024. https://www.unesco.org/en/legal-affairs/universal-declaration-bioethics-and-human-rights. Accessed January 9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. 2023. Summary on environment, climate change and health for WHO representatives and other country staff.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiesing, Urban. 2020. The hippocratic oath and the declaration of Geneva: legitimisation attempts of professional conduct. Medicine Health Care and Philosophy 23: 81&#x2013;86. 10.1007/s11019-019-09910-w. 10.1007/s11019-019-09910-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11019-019-09910-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31197536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiesing, Urban. 2022. Climate change and the different roles of physicians: a critical response to a Planetary Health Pledge for Health Professionals in the Anthropocene. Medicine Health Care and Philosophy 25: 161&#x2013;164. 10.1007/s11019-021-10051-2. 10.1007/s11019-021-10051-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11019-021-10051-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8443911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34529217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilkinson, Alex, Ashley Woodcock. 2022. The environmental impact of inhalers for asthma: a green challenge and a golden opportunity. British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology 88: 3016&#x2013;3022. 10.1111/bcp.15135. 10.1111/bcp.15135</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bcp.15135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34719810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilkinson, Dominic. 2023. The harm principle, personal identity and identity-relative paternalism. Journal of Medical Ethics 49 Institute of Medical Ethics 393&#x2013;402. 10.1136/jme-2022-108418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10313974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36669884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zielinski, Chris. 2022. COP27 climate change conference: urgent action needed for Africa and the world. Journal of Medical Ethics 48. Institute of Medical Ethics: e2&#x2013;e2. 10.1136/jme-2022-108698.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9726951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36257792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>