<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38745233</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1472-6955</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>May</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC nursing</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Developing a survey to measure nursing students' knowledge, attitudes and beliefs, influences, and willingness to be involved in Medical Assistance in Dying (MAiD): a mixed method modified e-Delphi study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>326</StartPage><MedlinePgn>326</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">326</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12912-024-01984-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Medical Assistance in Dying (MAiD) was legalized in Canada in 2016. Canada's legislation is the first to permit Nurse Practitioners (NP) to serve as independent MAiD assessors and providers. Registered Nurses' (RN) also have important roles in MAiD that include MAiD care coordination; client and family teaching and support, MAiD procedural quality; healthcare provider and public education; and bereavement care for family. Nurses have a right under the law to conscientious objection to participating in MAiD. Therefore, it is essential to prepare nurses in their entry-level education for the practice implications and moral complexities inherent in this practice. Knowing what nursing students think about MAiD is a critical first step. Therefore, the purpose of this study was to develop a survey to measure nursing students' knowledge, attitudes and beliefs, influences, and willingness to be involved in MAiD in the Canadian context.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The design was a mixed-method, modified e-Delphi method that entailed item generation from the literature, item refinement through a 2 round survey of an expert faculty panel, and item validation through a cognitive focus group interview with nursing students. The settings were a University located in an urban area and a College located in a rural area in Western Canada.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">During phase 1, a 56-item survey was developed from existing literature that included demographic items and items designed to measure experience with death and dying (including MAiD), education and preparation, attitudes and beliefs, influences on those beliefs, and anticipated future involvement. During phase 2, an expert faculty panel reviewed, modified, and prioritized the items yielding 51 items. During phase 3, a sample of nursing students further evaluated and modified the language in the survey to aid readability and comprehension. The final survey consists of 45 items including 4 case studies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Systematic evaluation of knowledge-to-date coupled with stakeholder perspectives supports robust survey design. This study yielded a survey to assess nursing students' attitudes toward MAiD in a Canadian context.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The survey is appropriate for use in education and research to measure knowledge and attitudes about MAiD among nurse trainees and can be a helpful step in preparing nursing students for entry-level practice.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schroeder</LastName><ForeName>Jocelyn</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health and Human Services, Selkirk College, Castlegar, BC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pesut</LastName><ForeName>Barbara</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health and Human Services, Selkirk College, Castlegar, BC, Canada. Barb.pesut@ubc.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, University of British Columbia Okanagan, Kelowna, BC, Canada. Barb.pesut@ubc.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Olsen</LastName><ForeName>Lise</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, University of British Columbia Okanagan, Kelowna, BC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oelke</LastName><ForeName>Nelly D</ForeName><Initials>ND</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, University of British Columbia Okanagan, Kelowna, BC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharp</LastName><ForeName>Helen</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, University of British Columbia Okanagan, Kelowna, BC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088683</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6955</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Canada</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">End of life care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Euthanasia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medical assistance in dying (MAiD)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nursing education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Student nurses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Survey</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38745233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11092000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12912-024-01984-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12912-024-01984-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Nicol J, Tiedemann M. Legislative Summary: Bill C-14: An Act to amend the Criminal Code and to make related amendments to other Acts (medical assistance in dying). Available from: https://lop.parl.ca/staticfiles/PublicWebsite/Home/ResearchPublications/LegislativeSummaries/PDF/42-1/c14-e.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Downie J, Scallion K. Foreseeably unclear. The meaning of the &#x201c;reasonably foreseeable&#x201d; criterion for access to medical assistance in dying in Canada. Dalhousie Law J. 2018;41(1):23&#x2013;57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicol J, Tiedeman M. Legislative summary of Bill C-7: an act to amend the criminal code (medical assistance in dying) Ottawa: Government of Canada; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Council of Canadian Academies. The state of knowledge on medical assistance in dying where a mental disorder is the sole underlying medical condition. Ottawa; 2018. Available from: https://cca-reports.ca/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-State-of-Knowledge-on-Medical-Assistance-in-Dying-Where-a-Mental-Disorder-is-the-Sole-Underlying-Medical-Condition.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Council of Canadian Academies. The state of knowledge on advance requests for medical assistance in dying. Ottawa; 2018. Available from: https://cca-reports.ca/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/The-State-of-Knowledge-on-Advance-Requests-for-Medical-Assistance-in-Dying.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Council of Canadian Academies. The state of knowledge on medical assistance in dying for mature minors. Ottawa; 2018. Available from: https://cca-reports.ca/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/The-State-of-Knowledge-on-Medical-Assistance-in-Dying-for-Mature-Minors.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Canada. Third annual report on medical assistance in dying in Canada 2021. Ottawa; 2022. [cited 2023 Oct 23]. Available from: https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/services/medical-assistance-dying/annual-report-2021.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banner D, Schiller CJ, Freeman S. Medical assistance in dying: a political issue for nurses and nursing in Canada. Nurs Philos. 2019;20(4):e12281. doi: 10.1111/nup.12281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nup.12281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31478340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pesut B, Thorne S, Stager ML, Schiller CJ, Penney C, Hoffman C, et al. Medical assistance in dying: a review of Canadian nursing regulatory documents. Policy Polit Nurs Pract. 2019;20(3):113&#x2013;130. doi: 10.1177/1527154419845407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1527154419845407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6827351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31060478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>College of Registered Nurses of British Columbia. Scope of practice for registered nurses [Internet]. Vancouver; 2018. Available from: https://www.bccnm.ca/Documents/standards_practice/rn/RN_ScopeofPractice.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pesut B, Thorne S, Schiller C, Greig M, Roussel J, Tishelman C. Constructing good nursing practice for medical assistance in dying in Canada: an interpretive descriptive study. Global Qual Nurs Res. 2020;7:2333393620938686. doi: 10.1177/2333393620938686.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/2333393620938686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7377599</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32743024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pesut B, Thorne S, Schiller CJ, Greig M, Roussel J. The rocks and hard places of MAiD: a qualitative study of nursing practice in the context of legislated assisted death. BMC Nurs. 2020;19:12. doi: 10.1186/s12912-020-0404-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12912-020-0404-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7025406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32095114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pesut B, Greig M, Thorne S, Burgess M, Storch JL, Tishelman C, et al. Nursing and euthanasia: a narrative review of the nursing ethics literature. Nurs Ethics. 2020;27(1):152&#x2013;167. doi: 10.1177/0969733019845127.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0969733019845127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7323743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31113279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pesut B, Thorne S, Storch J, Chambaere K, Greig M, Burgess M. Riding an elephant: a qualitative study of nurses' moral journeys in the context of Medical Assistance in Dying (MAiD) Journal Clin Nurs. 2020;29(19&#x2013;20):3870&#x2013;3881. doi: 10.1111/jocn.15427.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jocn.15427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7540490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32700402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamb C, Babenko-Mould Y, Evans M, Wong CA, Kirkwood KW. Conscientious objection and nurses: results of an interpretive phenomenological study. Nurs Ethics. 2018;26(5):1337&#x2013;1349. doi: 10.1177/0969733018763996.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0969733018763996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29614913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wright DK, Chan LS, Fishman JR, Macdonald ME. "Reflection and soul searching:" Negotiating nursing identity at the fault lines of palliative care and medical assistance in dying. Social Sci &amp; Med. 2021;289:114366. doi: 10.1016/j.socscimed.2021.114366.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2021.114366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34624622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beuthin R, Bruce A, Scaia M. Medical assistance in dying (MAiD): Canadian nurses&#x2019; experiences. Nurs Forum. 2018;54(4):511&#x2013;520. doi: 10.1111/nuf.12280.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nuf.12280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6282783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29972596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruce A, Beuthin R. Medically assisted dying in Canada: "Beautiful Death" is transforming nurses' experiences of suffering. The Canadian J Nurs Res | Revue Canadienne de Recherche en Sci Infirmieres. 2020;52(4):268&#x2013;77. 10.1177/0844562119856234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31188639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canadian Nurses Association. Code of ethics for registered nurses. Ottawa; 2017. Available from: https://www.cna-aiic.ca/en/nursing/regulated-nursing-in-canada/nursing-ethics.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canadian Nurses Association. National nursing framework on Medical Assistance in Dying in Canada. Ottawa: 2017. Available from: https://www.virtualhospice.ca/Assets/cna-national-nursing-framework-on-maidEng_20170216155827.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pesut B, Thorne S, Greig M. Shades of gray: conscientious objection in medical assistance in dying. Nursing Inq. 2020;27(1):e12308. doi: 10.1111/nin.12308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nin.12308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7027545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31273903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durojaiye A, Ryan R, Doody O. Student nurse education and preparation for palliative care: a scoping review. PLoS ONE. 2023 doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0286678.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0286678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10317240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37399170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMechan C, Bruce A, Beuthin R. Canadian nursing students&#x2019; experiences with medical assistance in dying | Les exp&#xe9;riences d&#x2019;&#xe9;tudiantes en sciences infirmi&#xe8;res au regard de l&#x2019;aide m&#xe9;dicale &#xe0; mourir. Qual Adv Nurs Educ - Avanc&#xe9;es en Formation Infirmi&#xe8;re. 2019;5(1). 10.17483/2368-6669.1179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adler M, Ziglio E. Gazing into the oracle. The Delphi method and its application to social policy and public health. London: Jessica Kingsley Publishers; 1996</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeney S, Hasson F, McKenna H. Consulting the oracle: ten lessons from using the Delphi technique in nursing research. J Adv Nurs. 2006;53(2):205&#x2013;212. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2648.2006.03716.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2648.2006.03716.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16422719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeney S, Hasson F, McKenna H. The Delphi technique in nursing and health research. 1st ed. City: Wiley; 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willis GB. Cognitive interviewing: a tool for improving questionnaire design. 1st ed. Thousand Oaks, Calif: Sage; 2005. ISBN: 9780761928041</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamb C, Evans M, Babenko-Mould Y, Wong CA, Kirkwood EW. Conscience, conscientious objection, and nursing: a concept analysis. Nurs Ethics. 2017;26(1):37&#x2013;49. doi: 10.1177/0969733017700236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0969733017700236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28399688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamb C, Evans M, Babenko-Mould Y, Wong CA, Kirkwood K. Nurses&#x2019; use of conscientious objection and the implications of conscience. J Adv Nurs. 2018;75(3):594&#x2013;602. doi: 10.1111/jan.13869.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jan.13869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30328136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Vaus D. Surveys in social research. 6. Abingdon, Oxon: Routledge; 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boateng GO, Neilands TB, Frongillo EA, Melgar-Qui&#xf1;onez HR, Young SL. Best practices for developing and validating scales for health, social, and behavioral research: A primer. Front Public Health. 2018;6:149. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2018.00149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2018.00149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6004510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29942800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puchta C, Potter J. Focus group practice. 1. London: Sage; 2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Streiner DL, Norman GR, Cairney J. Health measurement scales: a practical guide to their development and use. 5. Oxford: Oxford University Press; 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsieh H-F, Shannon SE. Three approaches to qualitative content analysis. Qual Health Res. 2005;15(9):1277&#x2013;1288. doi: 10.1177/1049732305276687.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1049732305276687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16204405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adesina O, DeBellis A, Zannettino L. Third-year Australian nursing students' attitudes, experiences, knowledge, and education concerning end-of-life care. Int J of Palliative Nurs. 2014;20(8):395&#x2013;401. doi: 10.12968/ijpn.2014.20.8.395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12968/ijpn.2014.20.8.395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25151867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bator EX, Philpott B, Costa AP. This moral coil: a cross-sectional survey of Canadian medical student attitudes toward medical assistance in dying. BMC Med Ethics. 2017;18(1):58. doi: 10.1186/s12910-017-0218-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12910-017-0218-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5658957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29078769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beuthin R, Bruce A, Scaia M. Medical assistance in dying (MAiD): Canadian nurses&#x2019; experiences. Nurs Forum. 2018;53(4):511&#x2013;520. doi: 10.1111/nuf.12280.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nuf.12280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6282783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29972596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown J, Goodridge D, Thorpe L, Crizzle A. What is right for me, is not necessarily right for you: the endogenous factors influencing nonparticipation in medical assistance in dying. Qual Health Res. 2021;31(10):1786&#x2013;1800.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8446887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33938306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falconer J, Couture F, Demir KK, Lang M, Shefman Z, Woo M. Perceptions and intentions toward medical assistance in dying among Canadian medical students. BMC Med Ethics. 2019;20(1):22. doi: 10.1186/s12910-019-0356-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12910-019-0356-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6444527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30940195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green G, Reicher S, Herman M, Raspaolo A, Spero T, Blau A. Attitudes toward euthanasia&#x2014;dual view: Nursing students and nurses. Death Stud. 2022;46(1):124&#x2013;131. doi: 10.1080/07481187.2020.1716887.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/07481187.2020.1716887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31983300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosseinzadeh K, Rafiei H. Nursing student attitudes toward euthanasia: a cross-sectional study. Nurs Ethics. 2019;26(2):496&#x2013;503. doi: 10.1177/0969733017718393.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0969733017718393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28748741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozcelik H, Tekir O, Samancioglu S, Fadiloglu C, Ozkara E. Nursing students' approaches toward euthanasia. Omega (Westport) 2014;69(1):93&#x2013;103. doi: 10.2190/OM.69.1.f.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2190/OM.69.1.f</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25084711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canning SE, Drew C. Canadian nursing students&#x2019; understanding, and comfort levels related to medical assistance in dying. Qual Adv Nurs Educ - Avanc&#xe9;es en Formation Infirmi&#xe8;re. 2022;8(2). 10.17483/2368-6669.1326.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edo-Gual M, Tom&#xe1;s-S&#xe1;bado J, Bardallo-Porras D, Monforte-Royo C. The impact of death and dying on nursing students: an explanatory model. J Clin Nurs. 2014;23(23&#x2013;24):3501&#x2013;3512. doi: 10.1111/jocn.12602.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jocn.12602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24698364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman LA, Pfaff KA, Kopchek L, Liebman J. Investigating palliative care nurse attitudes towards medical assistance in dying: an exploratory cross-sectional study. J Adv Nurs. 2020;76(2):535&#x2013;545. doi: 10.1111/jan.14252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jan.14252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31650568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown J, Goodridge D, Thorpe L, Crizzle A. &#x201c;I am okay with it, but I am not going to do it:&#x201d; the exogenous factors influencing non-participation in medical assistance in dying. Qual Health Res. 2021;31(12):2274&#x2013;2289. doi: 10.1177/10497323211027130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/10497323211027130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8564235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34238079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dimoula M, Kotronoulas G, Katsaragakis S, Christou M, Sgourou S, Patiraki E. Undergraduate nursing students' knowledge about palliative care and attitudes towards end-of-life care: A three-cohort, cross-sectional survey. Nurs Educ Today. 2019;74:7&#x2013;14. doi: 10.1016/j.nedt.2018.11.025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nedt.2018.11.025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30554033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matchim Y, Raetong P. Thai nursing students' experiences of caring for patients at the end of life: a phenomenological study. Int J Palliative Nurs. 2018;24(5):220&#x2013;229. doi: 10.12968/ijpn.2018.24.5.220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12968/ijpn.2018.24.5.220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29792768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canadian Institute for Health Research. Sex and gender in health research [Internet]. Ottawa: CIHR; 2021 [cited 2023 Oct 23]. Available from: https://cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/50833.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canadian Nurses&#x2019; Association. Nursing statistics. Ottawa: CNA; 2023 [cited 2023 Oct 23]. Available from: https://www.cna-aiic.ca/en/nursing/regulated-nursing-in-canada/nursing-statistics.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krumpal I. Determinants of social desirability bias in sensitive surveys: a literature review. Qual Quant. 2013;47(4):2025&#x2013;2047. doi: 10.1007/s11135-011-9640-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11135-011-9640-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferri P, Di Lorenzo R, Stifani S, Morotti E, Vagnini M, Jim&#xe9;nez Herrera MF, et al. Nursing student attitudes toward dying patient care: a European multicenter cross-sectional study. Acta Bio Medica Atenei Parmensis. 2021;92(S2):e2021018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8138802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33855982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beuthin R, Bruce A. Medical assistance in dying (MAiD): Ten things leaders need to know. Nurs Leadership. 2018;31(4):74&#x2013;81. doi: 10.12927/cjnl.2019.25753.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12927/cjnl.2019.25753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30860972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thiele T, Dunsford J. Nurse leaders' role in medical assistance in dying: a relational ethics approach. Nurs Ethics. 2019;26(4):993&#x2013;999. doi: 10.1177/0969733017730684.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0969733017730684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28946798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>