<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39012365</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1557-1920</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jul</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of immigrant and minority health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Immigr Minor Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Experiences of Migrant Care Workers in Long-term Care Facilities: A Scoping Review.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10903-024-01618-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The employment of migrant care workers provides a remedy to face the challenges of increased demand for care of older adults. A scoping review aimed to identify, categorize, and summarize the existing knowledge about migrant care workers' working experiences in long-term care facilities. Identifying gaps in the literature can inform future research. Five electronic databases were searched in April 2024 in addition to a manual search for articles published in English. Forty-five articles were reviewed. A few studies described migrant care assistants' main tasks as assisting physical care and care assistants' characteristics grouped into personal and acquired qualities to provide good quality care. Migrant care workers experienced work satisfaction, achievement, adaptability and adjustment, organizational support, work burden, sense of loneliness, low wages, low social status, and loss of profession. They faced challenges involving inadequate knowledge of palliative care, communication and language barriers, cultural and religious differences, and health concerns. Friendly and discriminatory relationships were found between migrant care workers and stakeholders. Existing evidence regarding the experiences of migrant care workers in delivering palliative care to dying residents or facilitating death preparation is limited. Additionally, there is a notable absence of data from the perspectives of employers and residents on discrimination issues. Further research is necessary to investigate these areas.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huynh</LastName><ForeName>Nhien Thi Thuy</ForeName><Initials>NTT</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0009-2657-2940</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Medicine and Pharmacy at Ho Chi Minh City, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Le</LastName><ForeName>Thi Dung</ForeName><Initials>TD</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-2987-0608</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, College of Medicine, National Cheng Kung University, 1 University Road, Tainan, 70101, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hapsari</LastName><ForeName>Happy Indri</ForeName><Initials>HI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kusuma Husada University, Surakarta, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hsiao</LastName><ForeName>Hua-Tsen</ForeName><Initials>HT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, National Tainan Junior College of Nursing, Tainan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Mei-Chih</ForeName><Initials>MC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3228-4998</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, College of Medicine, National Cheng Kung University, 1 University Road, Tainan, 70101, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, National Tainan Junior College of Nursing, Tainan, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kao</LastName><ForeName>Chi-Yin</ForeName><Initials>CY</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5510-6668</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, College of Medicine, National Cheng Kung University, 1 University Road, Tainan, 70101, Taiwan. chiyinkao@mail.ncku.edu.tw.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>The National Cheng Kung University Distinguished International Student Scholarship</GrantID><Agency>The National Cheng Kung University Distinguished International Student Scholarship</Agency><Country/></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Immigr Minor Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101256527</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1557-1912</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Care assistants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Long-term care facilities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Migrant care workers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nurses</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39012365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10903-024-01618-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10903-024-01618-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>WHO. Ageing and health 2021 [cited 2021 January 2021]; https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/ageing-and-health .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H-H, Tsay S-F. Elderly and long-term care trends and policy in Taiwan: challenges and opportunities for health care professionals. Kaohsiung J Med Sci. 2012;28(9):465&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22974664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.kjms.2012.04.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norton EC. Chapter 16 - Health and Long-Term Care, in Handbook of the Economics of Population Aging, J. Piggott and A. Woodland, Editors. 2016, North-Holland. pp. 951&#x2013;989.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OECD. Chapter 10. Ageing and long-term care in. Health at a glance 2021. OECD Publishing: Paris; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu C-S, Rong J-R. Relocation experiences of the elderly to a long-term care facility in Taiwan: a qualitative study. BMC Geriatr. 2020;20(1):280.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32762717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7409483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12877-020-01679-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>OECD. Who cares? Attracting and retaining care workers for the elderly. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sowa-Kofta A, Rodrigues R, Lamura G, Sopadzhiyan A, Wittenberg R, Bauer G, et al. Long-term care and migrant care work: addressing workforce shortages while raising questions for European countries. Eurohealth. 2019;25(4):15&#x2013;8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres S, Lindblom J. Migrant care workers in elderly care: what a study of media representations suggests about Sweden as a caring democracy. Int J Ageing Later Life. 2020;14(2):61&#x2013;87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Labor Organization. C143&#x2013;Migrant Workers (Supplementary Provisions) Convention, 1975 (No. 143). 1975 [cited 2022 25 May ]; https://www.ilo.org/dyn/normlex/en/f?p=NORMLEXPUB:12100:0::NO::P12100_INSTRUMENT_ID:312288 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ow Yong B, Manthorpe J. The experiences of Indian migrant care home staff working with people with dementia: a pilot study exploring cultural perspectives. Working Older People: Community Care Policy Pract. 2016;20(1):3&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/WWOP-07-2015-0012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nichols P, Horner B, Fyfe K. Understanding and improving communication processes in an increasingly multicultural aged care workforce. J Aging Stud. 2015;32:23&#x2013;31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25661853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaging.2014.12.003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khatutsky G, Wiener JM, Anderson WL. Immigrant and non-immigrant certified nursing assistants in nursing homes: how do they differ? J Aging Soc Policy. 2010;22(3):267&#x2013;87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20589554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/08959420.2010.485526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Timonen V, Doyle M. Caring and collaborating across cultures? Migrant care workers&#x2019; relationships with care recipients, colleagues and employers. Eur J Women&#x2019;s Stud. 2010;17(1):25&#x2013;41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1350506809350859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebayo B, Nichols P, Heslop K, Brijnath B. A scoping review of Dementia Care experiences in migrant aged care workforce. Gerontologist. 2020;60(2):e105&#x2013;16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30977793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iecovich E. Sources of stress and conflicts between Elderly patients, their family members and personnel in Care settings. J Gerontol Soc Work. 2000;34(2):73&#x2013;88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1300/J083v34n02_07</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng Chok H, Mannix J, Dickson C, Wilkes L. The factors impacting personal and professional experiences of migrant nurses in Australia: an integrative review. Collegian. 2018;25(2):247&#x2013;53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.colegn.2017.06.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cangiano A. Elder care and Migrant Labor in Europe: a demographic Outlook. Popul Dev Rev, 2014. 40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arksey H, O&#x2019;Malley L. Scoping studies: towards a methodological framework. Int J Soc Res Methodol. 2005;8(1):19&#x2013;32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/1364557032000119616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salami B, Duggleby W, Rajani F. The perspective of employers/families and care recipients of migrant live-in caregivers: a scoping review. Health Soc Care Community. 2017;25(6):1667&#x2013;78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26910139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/hsc.12330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Overgaard C, Withers M, McDermott J. What do we know about the experiences of migrant care workers in Australia? A scoping study. Australian Journal of Social Issues; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tricco AC, Lillie E, Zarin W, O&#x2019;Brien KK, Colquhoun H, Levac D, et al. PRISMA Extension for scoping reviews (PRISMA-ScR): Checklist and Explanation. Ann Intern Med. 2018;169(7):467&#x2013;73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30178033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/M18-0850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peters MDJ, Godfrey CM, Khalil H, McInerney P, Parker D, Soares CB. Guidance for conducting systematic scoping reviews. Int J Evid Based Healthc. 2015;13(3):141&#x2013;6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26134548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/XEB.0000000000000050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peters M, Godfrey C, McInerney P, Munn Z, Trico A, Khalil H. In: Aromataris E, Munn Z, editors. Scoping reviews (2020 version), in JBI Manual for evidence synthesis. Editors: JBI; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sloane PD, Williams CS, Zimmerman S. Immigrant status and intention to leave of nursing assistants in U.S. nursing homes. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2010;58(4):731&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20398155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2010.02781.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryosho N. Experiences of racism by female minority and immigrant nursing assistants. Affilia: J Women Social Work. 2011;26(1):59&#x2013;71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0886109910392519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berdes C, Eckert JM. Race relations and caregiving relationships: a qualitative examination of perspectives from residents and nurse&#x2019;s aides in three nursing homes. Res Aging. 2001;23(1):109&#x2013;26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0164027501231006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher LT, Wallhagen MI. Day-to-day care: the interplay of CNA&#x2019;s views of residents and nursing home environments. J Gerontol Nurs. 2008;34(11):26&#x2013;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19024427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3928/00989134-20081101-04</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Showers F. Learning to care: work experiences and identity formation among African immigrant care workers in the US. Int J Care Caring. 2018;2(1):7&#x2013;25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1332/239788218X15187914933434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acker K, Pletz AM, Katz A, Hagopian A. Foreign-born care givers in Washington State nursing homes: characteristics, associations with quality of care, and views of administrators. J Aging Health. 2015;27(4):650&#x2013;69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25359766</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0898264314556618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebayo B, Durey A, Slack-Smith LM. Culturally and linguistically diverse (CALD) carers&#x2019; perceptions of oral care in residential aged care settings in Perth, Western Australia. Gerodontology. 2017;34(1):33&#x2013;41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26763582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ger.12219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goel K, Penman J. Employment experiences of immigrant workers in aged care in regional South Australia. Rural Remote Health, 2015. 15(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao F, Tilse C, Wilson J, Tuckett A, Newcombe P. Perceptions and employment intentions among aged care nurses and nursing assistants from diverse cultural backgrounds: a qualitative interview study. J Aging Stud. 2015;35:111&#x2013;22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26568221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaging.2015.08.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shrestha S, Wells Y, While C. Caring behaviours of culturally diverse personal care attendants from the perspective of older people living in residential aged care settings. Volume 51. New York, N.Y.): Geriatric Nursing; 2023. pp. 429&#x2013;38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebayo B, Nichols P, Heslop K, Brijnath B. Migrant care workers&#x2019; perceptions of their Working conditions in Australian residential aged care facilities. J Transcult Nurs. 2023;34(3):229&#x2013;37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37070577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10114248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/10436596231152204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aboderin I. Contexts, motives and experiences of Nigerian overseas nurses: understanding links to globalization. J Clin Nurs. 2007;16(12):2237&#x2013;45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18036114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2702.2007.01999.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adhikari R, Melia KM. The (mis)management of migrant nurses in the UK: a sociological study. J Nurs Adm Manag. 2015;23(3):359&#x2013;67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jonm.12141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nwakasi CC, Hayes C, Fulton J, Roberts AR. A pilot qualitative study of dementia perceptions of Nigerian migrant caregivers. Int J Afr Nurs Sci. 2019;10:167&#x2013;74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olasunkanmi-Alimi T, Natalier K, Mulholland M. African migrant women in the aged care sector: conceptualising experiences of racism, micro-aggressions and otherness. Journal of Sociology; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solum EM, Viken B, Lyberg A. First Year&#x2019;s work experiences of Foreign Educated nurses coming to Norway from other European Countries. SAGE Open Nursing; 2020. p. 6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munkejord MC. I work with my heart&#x2019;: experiences of migrant care workers in a Northern, Rural Context. J Popul Ageing. 2017;10(3):229&#x2013;46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12062-016-9157-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tingvold L, Fagertun A. Between privileged and oppressed? Immigrant labor trajectories in Norwegian long-term care. Sustainability 2020. 12(11).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavik M, Gripsrud B, Ramvi E. How do migrant nursing home staff relate to religion in their work with patients who are approaching death. J Holist Nurs. 2021;39(3):270&#x2013;1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0898010120973544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asis E, Carandang RR. The plight of migrant care workers in Japan: a qualitative study of their stressors on caregiving. J Migration Health. 2020;1:100001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34405157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jmh.2020.100001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Efendi F, Chen CM, Kurniati A, Arief YS, Ogawa R. The course of broken dreams: the expectations and realities of the life of Indonesian nurses as care workers in Japan. Collegian. 2022;29(5):680&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.colegn.2022.04.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurniati A, Chen CM, Efendi F, Ogawa R. A deskilling and challenging journey: the lived experience of Indonesian nurse returnees. Int Nurs Rev. 2017;64(4):494&#x2013;501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28168716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/inr.12352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navallo K. Let my hands be your hands: Constructions of intimacy among Filipina migrants in the care of the elderly in Japan. Gend Work Organ. 2022;29(3):938&#x2013;52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/gwao.12763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angus E, Reid K, Yamit S, Coe G, Ryan B, Crichton S. Experience of internationally qualified nurses providing palliative care in a New Zealand aged residential care facility. Int J Palliat Nurs. 2021;27(10):515&#x2013;23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34919417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12968/ijpn.2021.27.10.515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenkins B, Huntington A. We are the international nurses: an exploration of internationally qualified nurses&#x2019; experiences of transitioning to New Zealand and working in aged care. Nurs Praxis New Z. 2016;32(2):9&#x2013;20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.36951/NgPxNZ.2016.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lovelock K, Martin G. Eldercare work, migrant care workers, affective care and subjective proximity. Ethn Health. 2016;21(4):379&#x2013;96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26222922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13557858.2015.1045407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngocha-Chaderopa NE, Boon B. Managing for quality aged residential care with a migrant workforce. J Manage Organ. 2016;22(1):32&#x2013;48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/jmo.2015.17</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu CY, Li YY, Lyver MJ. Elderly Caregiving Quality Improvement: a pilot study of the burdens of Vietnamese caregivers in Taiwan. Int J Environ Res Public Health, 2022. 19(10).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang FF, Yang HH. The effects of nationality differences and work stressors on work adjustment for foreign nurse aides. BMC Health Serv Res. 2011;11:192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21846402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3170596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1472-6963-11-192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin L-P, Wu T-Y, Lin J-D. Comparison of job burnout and life satisfaction between native and foreign female direct care workers in disability institutions. Work. 2015;52(4):803&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26409362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3233/WOR-152117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nursalam N, Chen C-M, Efendi F, Has, EMMa, Hidayati L, Hadisuyatmana S. The lived experiences of Indonesian nurses who worked as care workers in Taiwan. J Nurs Res. 2020;28(2):e78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31714449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/jnr.0000000000000355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lightman N. Caring during the COVID-19 crisis: intersectional exclusion of immigrant women health care aides in Canadian long-term care. Health Soc Care Community. 2022;30(4):e1343&#x2013;51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34396607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/hsc.13541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourgeault IL, Atanackovic J, Rashid A, Parpia R. Relations between immigrant care workers and older persons in home and long-term care. Can J Aging. 2010;29(1):109&#x2013;18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20202269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0714980809990407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novek S. Filipino health care aides and the nursing home labour market in Winnipeg. Can J Aging. 2013;32(4):405&#x2013;16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24063532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S071498081300038X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doyle M, Timonen V. The different faces of care work: understanding the experiences of the multi-cultural care workforce. Ageing Soc. 2009;29:337&#x2013;50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0144686X08007708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamrin SBD. Constructions of inclusion at two senior nursing home units in Sweden: immigrants&#x2019; perspectives. Equality Divers Inclusion. 2019;38(4):462&#x2013;76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/EDI-05-2018-0091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Storm P. Managers&#x2019; perceptions of masculinity and racialization in Swedish nursing homes. Gend Work Organ. 2023;30(6):2175&#x2013;87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/gwao.13063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen M, Shinan-Altman S. A cross-cultural study of nursing aides&#x2019; attitudes to elder abuse in nursing homes. Int Psychogeriatr. 2011;23(8):1213&#x2013;21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21429279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1041610211000391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ham A. First generation immigrant and native nurses enacting good care in a nursing home. Nurs Ethics. 2021;28(3):402&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32552426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0969733020921487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walsh K, Shutes I. Care relationships, quality of care and migrant workers caring for older people. Ageing Soc. 2013;33(3):393&#x2013;420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0144686X11001309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Storm P, Lowndes R. Yes, the guys can do it! Migrant male care workers in Canadian and Swedish nursing homes. Teorija Praksa. 2019;56(4):1052&#x2013;68.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>