<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39157418</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2632-3524</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>18</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Palliative care and social practice</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Palliat Care Soc Pract</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>'There is no such word as palliative care for us at the moment': A mixed-method study exploring the perceptions of healthcare professionals on the need for palliative care in Bhutan.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>26323524241272102</StartPage><MedlinePgn>26323524241272102</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">26323524241272102</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/26323524241272102</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The need for palliative care is ever-increasing globally. However, it is least developed or not available in most low-and-middle-income-countries including Bhutan.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study was aimed at exploring the perspectives of Bhutanese healthcare professionals on the need for palliative care in the country.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This is a cross-sectional, mixed-method study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SETTING/SUBJECTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The study sites included all levels of healthcare in Bhutan and involved doctors, nurses, physiotherapists, pharmacists, health assistants and <i>Drungtshos</i> (traditional physicians). Data were collected through surveys, focus group discussions and in-depth interviews.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">While the majority of the participants were directly involved in taking care of terminally ill and dying patients, only 14% had received some form of palliative care training for a duration ranging from 1&#x2009;day to 6&#x2009;weeks. Ninety-five percent of the participants reported that they faced challenges related to lack of palliative care knowledge and skills; limited resources including analgesics; shortage of doctors and nurses and lack of a palliative care team; issues with low illiteracy and financial challenges among patients; and policies and other systemic issues. The qualitative data generated four major themes: past adverse experiences; unique and complex needs for palliative care; challenges faced while caring for terminally ill and dying patients; and the urgent need for palliative care in Bhutan.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Bhutanese healthcare professionals had very limited exposure to palliative care. This study identified a crucial need for palliative care and informs the development of an appropriate palliative care model for Bhutan.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; The Author(s), 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Laabar</LastName><ForeName>Tara Devi</ForeName><Initials>TD</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0197-6884</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, Faculty of Nursing and Public Health, Khesar Gyalpo University of Medical Sciences of Bhutan, Thimphu, Bhutan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saunders</LastName><ForeName>Christobel</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgery, Melbourne Medical School, The University of Melbourne, Parkville, VIC, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Auret</LastName><ForeName>Kirsten</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Rural Clinical School of Western Australia, The University of Western Australia, Albany, WA, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Johnson</LastName><ForeName>Claire E</ForeName><Initials>CE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Australian Health Services Research Institute, University of Wollongong, Wollongong, NSW, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Palliat Care Soc Pract</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101754997</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2632-3524</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="plain-language-summary" Language="eng"><AbstractText>&#x2018;There is no such word as palliative care for us at the moment&#x2019;: A study exploring the perceptions of healthcare professionals on the need for palliative care in Bhutan Palliative care is least developed in most low-and-middle-income-countries. This study was aimed at exploring the perspectives of healthcare professionals on the need for palliative care in Bhutan. Utilising both quantitative and qualitative approaches, the study sites included all levels of healthcare in Bhutan and involved doctors, nurses, physiotherapists, pharmacists, health assistants and Drungtshos (traditional physicians). Data were collected through surveys, focus group discussions and in-depth interviews. While the majority of the participants were directly involved in taking care of terminally ill and dying patients, only 14% had received some form of palliative care training for a duration ranging from one day to six weeks. Ninety five percent of the participants reported that they faced challenges related to lack of palliative care knowledge and skills; limited resources including analgesics; shortage of doctors and nurses and lack of a palliative care team; issues with low illiteracy and financial challenges among patients; and policies and other systemic issues. The qualitative data generated four major themes: past adverse experiences; unique and complex needs for palliative care; challenges faced while caring for terminally ill and dying patients; and the urgent need for palliative care in Bhutan. Bhutanese healthcare professionals had very limited exposure to palliative care. This study identified a crucial need for palliative care and informs the development of an appropriate palliative care model for Bhutan.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; The Author(s), 2024.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bhutan</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">healthcare professionals</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mixed-method study</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">needs</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">palliative care</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39157418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11329896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/26323524241272102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_26323524241272102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Worldwide Hospice and Palliative Care Alliance and World Health Organization. Global atlas of palliative care. 2nd ed. London, UK: Worldwide Hospice Palliative Care Alliance, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stjernsward J, Foley KM, Ferris FD. The public health strategy for palliative care. J Pain Symptom Manage 2007; 33(5): 486&#x2013;493.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17482035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
World Health Organization. Palliative care key facts. WHO, https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/palliative-care (2021, accessed 26 October 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Connor SR, Gwyther E. The worldwide hospice palliative care alliance. J Pain Symptom Manage 2018; 55(2S): 112&#x2013;116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28797861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knaul FM, Farmer PE, Krakauer EL, et al.. Alleviating the access abyss in palliative care and pain relief &#x2013; an imperative of universal health coverage. The Lancet Commission Report. Lancet 2017; 391(10128): 1391&#x2013;1454.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29032993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
World Health Assembly. Strengthening of palliative care as a component of integrated treatment throughout the life course, http://apps.who.int/gb/ebwha/pdf_files/WHA67/A67_31-en.pdf (2014, accessed 23 April 2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24779434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Callaway MV, Connor SR, Foley KM. World Health Organization public health model: a roadmap for palliative care development. J Pain Symptom Manage 2018; 55(2S): 6&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28801003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Worldometer. Bhutan population (LIVE). Elaboration of data by United Nations, Department of Economic and Social Affairs, Population Division, https://www.worldometers.info/world-population/bhutan-population/ (2021, accessed 24 August 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Gross National Happiness Center Bhutan. What is GNH, http://www.gnhcentrebhutan.org/what-is-gnh/history-of-gnh/ (2018, accessed 10 April 2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thinley S, Tshering P, Wangmo K, et al.. The Kingdom of Bhutan health system review. New Delhi, India: WHO, 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
The World Bank. Life expectancy at birth, total (years) &#x2013; Bhutan, https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.DYN.LE00.IN?locations=BT (2021, accessed 16 July 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health. Annual health bulletin. Thimphu: HMIS and Research Section PaPDP, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health. BHUTAN cancer control strategy (2019&#x2013;2025). Thimphu: Ministry of Health, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laabar TD, Saunders C, Auret K, et al.. Palliative care needs among patients with advanced illnesses in Bhutan. BMC Palliat Care 2021; 20(8): 1&#x2013;10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7797114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33422058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laabar TD, Auret K, Saunders C, et al.. Support needs for Bhutanese family members taking care of loved ones diagnosed with advanced illness. J Palliat Care 2021; 37: 401&#x2013;409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34898330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Ministry of Health. Launch of palliative care by her royal highness Ashi Kesang Wangmo Wangchuck. Thimphu, Bhutan: Ministry of Health, Royal Government of Bhutan, http://www.moh.gov.bt/launch-of-palliative-care-by-her-royal-highness-ashi-kesang-wangmo-wangchuck/ (2020, accessed 30 November 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Ministry of Health. National Health Policy, https://www.moh.gov.bt/wp-content/uploads/moh-files/2015/11/National-Health-Policy.pdf (2015, accessed 18 December 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Creswell JW. Research design: qualitative, quantitative, and mixed methods approaches. 4th ed. London, United Kingdom: Sage Publications, Inc., 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wisdom J, Creswell JW. Mixed methods: integrating quantitative and qualitative data collection and analysis while studying patient-centered medical home models. Rockville, MD: Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, February 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong A, Sainsbury P, Craig J. Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ): a 32-item checklist for interviews and focus groups. Int J Qual Health Care 2007; 19(6): 349&#x2013;357</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17872937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laabar TD, Saunders C, Auret K, et al.. Socially, culturally and spiritually sensitive public health palliative care models in the lower-income countries: an integrative literature review. Indian J Palliat Care 2023; 29(1): 15&#x2013;27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9944658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36846282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>SAS Institute Inc. SAS/STAT&#xae; User&#x2019;s Guide. Cary, NC: SAS Institute Inc, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qual Res Psychol 2006; 3(2): 77&#x2013;101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peeler A, Afolabi O, Adcock M, et al.. Primary palliative care in low- and middle-income countries: a systematic review and thematic synthesis of the evidence for models and outcomes. Palliat Med. Epub ahead of print May 2024. DOI: 10.1177/02692163241248324.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/02692163241248324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38693716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamonyo ES. The Palliative care journey in Kenya and Uganda. J Pain Symptom Manage 2018; 55(2S): S46&#x2013;S54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28801004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosa WE, Male MA, Ntizimira CR, et al.. The advancement of palliative care in Rwanda: transnational partnerships and educational innovation. J Hosp Palliat Nurs 2018; 20(3): 304&#x2013;312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30063682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Planning and implementing palliative care services: a guide for programme managers. Gen&#xe8;ve, Switzerland: WHO, 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Ministry of Health. National essential medicines list 2018. Ministry of Health, Royal Government of Bhutan, http://www.moh.gov.bt/national-essential-medicines-list-2018/ (2018, accessed 4 June 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scholten WK, Christensen AE, Olesen AE, et al.. Quantifying the adequacy of opioid analgesic consumption globally: an updated method and early findings. Am J Public Health 2019; 109(1): 52&#x2013;58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6301424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30496006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Afolabi OA, Nkhoma K, Maddocks M, et al.. What constitutes a palliative care need in people with serious illnesses across Africa? A mixed-methods systematic review of the concept and evidence. Palliat Med 2021; 35: 1052&#x2013;1070.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8371282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33860715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S. Models of delivering palliative and end-of-life care in India. Curr Opin Support Palliat Care 2013; 7: 216&#x2013;222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23635881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
UNESCO Institute of Statistics. Bhutan: Education and Literacy. 2021.  [cited 2021 June 29]. Available from: http://uis.unesco.org/en/country/bt</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baider L, Surbone A. Cancer and the family: the silent words of truth. J Clin Oncol 2009; 28(7): 1269&#x2013;1272.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19917851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah SAM, Amjad S. Cultural diversity in Pakistan: national vs provincial. Mediterr J Social Sci 2011; 2(2): 331&#x2013;344.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jawaid M, Qamar B, Masood Z, et al.. Disclosure of cancer diagnosis: Pakistani patients&#x2019; perspective. Middle East J Cancer 2010; 1(2): 89&#x2013;94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrera E, Rocafort J, De Lima L, et al.. Regional palliative care program in Extremadura: an effective public health care model in a sparsely populated region. J Pain Symptom Manage 2007; 33(5): 591&#x2013;598.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17482053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Worldwide Palliative Care Alliance and World Health Organization. Global atlas of palliative care at the end of life, https://waltherglobalpalliativecare.iu.edu/resources/international-resources/doc-files/wpca_global_atlas_of_palliative_care_2014.pdf (2014, accessed 20 April 2018).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>