<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39152645</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1477-030X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Palliative medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Palliat Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The double awareness of the wish to hasten death and the will to live: A secondary analysis of outlier patients from a mixed-methods study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2692163241269689</StartPage><MedlinePgn>2692163241269689</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/02692163241269689</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Patients with serious illness frequently report (temporary) wishes to hasten death. Even until the end-of-life, many patients also harbor a will to live. Although both phenomena are negatively correlated according to some studies, they can also co-exist. Knowledge about the complex relationship between the seemingly opposing wish to hasten death and will to live is limited, but crucial for delivering adequate care and understanding potential requests for assisted dying.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">To study the correlation of and explore the relationship between wish to hasten death and will to live over 6&#x2009;weeks.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Observatory, prospective cohort study following a mixed methods design. Analysis of quantitative (Schedules of Attitudes Toward Hastened Death, a visual numerical scale and (additional) validated questionnaires) and qualitative (semi-structured interviews) data with illustrative case descriptions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SETTING/PARTICIPANTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Patients receiving palliative care with heterogenous underlying diseases from various care settings, before and after an open conversation on a possible desire to die.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In <i>n</i>&#x2009;=&#x2009;85 patients, wish to hasten death and will to live were strongly negatively correlated at three time points (baseline: <i>r</i>(65)&#x2009;=&#x2009;-0.647, <i>p</i>&#x2009;&#x2a7d;&#x2009;0.001; after 1&#x2009;week: <i>r</i>(55)&#x2009;=&#x2009;-0.457, <i>p</i>&#x2009;&#x2a7d;&#x2009;0.001 and after 4-6&#x2009;weeks: <i>r</i>(43)&#x2009;=&#x2009;-0.727, <i>p</i>&#x2009;&#x2a7d;&#x2009;0.001). However, visual assessment of scatterplots revealed a small, but substantial number of outliers. When focusing on these outlier patients, they showed clinically relevant changes between baseline and 6&#x2009;weeks with the wish to hasten death changing in <i>n</i>&#x2009;=&#x2009;9 (15% of <i>n</i>&#x2009;=&#x2009;60) and the will to live changing in <i>n</i>&#x2009;=&#x2009;11 (18.6% of <i>n</i>&#x2009;=&#x2009;59). Interview data of three outlier cases illustrates unusual trajectories and possible factors which may influence them.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">As they can co-exist in different possible combinations, a high wish to hasten death does not necessarily imply a low will to live and vice versa. Patients receiving palliative care can hold such seemingly opposing positions in mind as a form of coping when confronted with an existential threat of serious illness. Therefore, health professionals are encouraged to proactively engage patients in conversation about both phenomena.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bostr&#xf6;m</LastName><ForeName>Kathleen</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3159-6535</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Palliative Medicine, Faculty of Medicine and University Hospital, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dojan</LastName><ForeName>Thomas</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Palliative Medicine, Faculty of Medicine and University Hospital, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hellmich</LastName><ForeName>Martin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Statistics and Computational Biology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kremeike</LastName><ForeName>Kerstin</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4316-2379</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Palliative Medicine, Faculty of Medicine and University Hospital, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Voltz</LastName><ForeName>Raymond</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Palliative Medicine, Faculty of Medicine and University Hospital, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Integrated Oncology Aachen Bonn Cologne Duesseldorf (CIO ABCD), Faculty of Medicine and University Hospital, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Health Services Research, Faculty of Medicine and University Hospital, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Palliat Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8704926</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0269-2163</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wish to hasten death</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">correlation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">desire to die</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">end-of-life</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">will to live</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of conflicting interestThe author(s) declared the following potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: KB, TD, and KK declare no support from any organization for the submitted work; no financial relationships with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work in the previous 3&#x2009;years; no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work. RV reports grants from the Federal Ministry of Education and Research during the conduct of the study. Grants from the Federal Joint Committee (G-BA) Germany, Innovation Fund; EU&#x2014;Horizon 2020; Robert Bosch Foundation; Tr&#xe4;gerwerk Soziale Dienste in Sachsen GmbH; Association Endlich Palliativ &amp; Hospiz e.V.; Ministry of Labor, Health and Social Affairs of North Rhine-Westphalia; German Cancer Society, Association of the Scientific Medical Societies, German Cancer Aid; Ministry of Culture and Science of North Rhine-Westphalia; personal fees from AOK Health Insurance; German Cancer Society/National Health Academy (NGA); MSD Sharp &amp; Dome; Hertie Foundation and Roche Germany.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>15</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>15</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39152645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/02692163241269689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>