<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38737406</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2632-3524</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>18</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Palliative care and social practice</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Palliat Care Soc Pract</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Willingness to support neighbours practically or emotionally: a cross-sectional survey among the general public.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>26323524241249196</StartPage><MedlinePgn>26323524241249196</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">26323524241249196</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/26323524241249196</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Wider social networks are increasingly recognized for supporting people with care needs. Health-promoting initiatives around the end of life aim to foster these social connections but currently provide little insight into how willing people are to help neighbours facing support needs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study describes how willing people are to help neighbours who need support practically or emotionally, whether there is a difference in willingness depending on the type of support needed and what determines this willingness.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We applied a cross-sectional survey design.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We distributed 4400 questionnaires to a random sample of people aged &gt;15 across four municipalities in Flanders, Belgium. These surveys included attitudinal and experiential questions related to serious illness, caregiving and dying. Respondents rated their willingness (scale of 1-5) to provide support to different neighbours in hypothetical scenarios: (1) an older person in need of assistance and (2) a caregiver of a dying partner.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 2008 questionnaires were returned (45.6%). The average willingness to support neighbours was 3.41 (case 1) and 3.85 (case 2). Helping with groceries scored highest; cooking and keeping company scored lowest. Factors associated with higher willingness included an optimistic outlook about receiving support from others, family caregiving experience and prior volunteering around serious illness or dying.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">People are generally willing to support their neighbours who need help practically or emotionally, especially when they have prior experience with illness, death or dying and when they felt supported by different groups of people. Community-based models that build support around people with care needs could explore to what extent this willingness translates into durable community support. Initiatives promoting social connection and cohesion around serious illness, caregiving and dying may harness this potential through experiential learning.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; The Author(s), 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Quintiens</LastName><ForeName>Bert</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7029-6466</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>End-of-Life Care Research Group, Vrije Universiteit Brussel and Ghent University, Laarbeeklaan 103, Brussels 1090, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smets</LastName><ForeName>Tinne</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>End-of-Life Care Research Group, Vrije Universiteit Brussel and Ghent University, Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chambaere</LastName><ForeName>Kenneth</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>End-of-Life Care Research Group, Vrije Universiteit Brussel and Ghent University, Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Van den Block</LastName><ForeName>Lieve</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>End-of-Life Care Research Group, Vrije Universiteit Brussel and Ghent University, Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deliens</LastName><ForeName>Luc</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8158-2422</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>End-of-Life Care Research Group, Vrije Universiteit Brussel and Ghent University, Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cohen</LastName><ForeName>Joachim</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>End-of-Life Care Research Group, Vrije Universiteit Brussel and Ghent University, Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Palliat Care Soc Pract</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101754997</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2632-3524</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">community involvement</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">end of life</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">experiential learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">family care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">new public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">social capital</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38737406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11085024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/26323524241249196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_26323524241249196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abel J, Walter T, Carey LB, et al.. Circles of care: should community development redefine the practice of palliative care? BMJ Support Palliat Care 2013; 3: 383&#x2013;388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24950517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Barrett P, Hale B, Butler M. Family care and social capital: transitions in informal care [Internet]. Dordrecht: Springer Netherlands, http://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-94-007-6872-7 (2014, accessed 26 July 2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-94-007-6872-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
United Nations. Expert group meeting on care and older persons: links to decent work, migration and gender. [Internet]. United Nations UN Department of Economic and Social Affairs, https://www.un.org/development/desa/ageing/wp-content/uploads/sites/24/2018/03/17-EGM-Care-Report-7-March-2018.pdf (2017, accessed 10 March 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lapierre TA, Keating N. Characteristics and contributions of non-kin carers of older people: a closer look at friends and neighbours. Ageing Soc 2013;33: 1442&#x2013;1468.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pleschberger S, Wosko P. From neighbour to carer: an exploratory study on the role of non-kin-carers in end-of-life care at home for older people living alone. Palliat Med 2017;31: 559&#x2013;565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27609606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
European Commission. Directorate General for Employment, Social Affairs and Inclusion, London School of Economics, and Political Science (LSE). Informal care in Europe: exploring formalisation, availability and quality [Internet]. Publications Office, https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2767/78836 (2018, accessed 8 March 2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2767/78836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knowles S, Combs R, Kirk S, et al.. Hidden caring, hidden carers? Exploring the experience of carers for people with long-term conditions. Health Soc Care Community 2016; 24: 203&#x2013;213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4744729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25706665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayo AM, Siegle K, Savell E, et al.. Lay caregivers&#x2019; experiences with caring for persons with dementia: a phenomenological study. J Gerontol Nurs 2020; 46: 17&#x2013;27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8915949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32491183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sallnow L, Smith R, Ahmedzai SH, et al.. Report of the Lancet Commission on the value of death: bringing death back into life. Lancet 2022; 399: 837&#x2013;884.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8803389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35114146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peeler A, Doran A, Winter-Dean L, et al.. Public health palliative care interventions that enable communities to support people who are dying and their carers: a scoping review of studies that assess person-centered outcomes. Front Public Health 2023; 11: 1180571.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10410270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37564426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sallnow L, Richardson H, Murray SA, et al.. The impact of a new public health approach to end-of-life care: a systematic review. Palliat Med 2016; 30: 200&#x2013;211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26269324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quintiens B, D&#x2019;Eer L, Deliens L, et al.. Area-based compassionate communities: a systematic integrative review of existing initiatives worldwide. Palliat Med 2022; 36: 422&#x2013;442.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35354413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glynn LG, Valderas JM, Healy P, et al.. The prevalence of multimorbidity in primary care and its effect on health care utilization and cost. Fam Pract 2011; 28: 516&#x2013;523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21436204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnett K, Mercer SW, Norbury M, et al.. Epidemiology of multimorbidity and implications for health care, research, and medical education: a cross-sectional study. Lancet 2012; 380: 37&#x2013;43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22579043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cassell A, Edwards D, Harshfield A, et al.. The epidemiology of multimorbidity in primary care: a retrospective cohort study. Br J Gen Pract 2018; 68: e245&#x2013;e251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5863678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29530918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development. Old-age dependency ratio [Internet], 2024, https://data.oecd.org/pop/old-age-dependency-ratio.htm (accessed 18 January 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen J, Deliens L. (ed.) A public health perspective on end of life care. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar SK. Kerala, India: a regional community-based palliative care model. J Pain Symptom Manage 2007; 33: 623&#x2013;627.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17482058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoefman RJ, Meulenkamp TM, De Jong JD. Who is responsible for providing care? Investigating the role of care tasks and past experiences in a cross-sectional survey in the Netherlands. BMC Health Serv Res 2017; 17: 477.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5505036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28697752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jegermalm M, Torg&#xe9; CJ. Three caregiver profiles: who are they, what do they do, and who are their co-carers? Eur J Soc Work 2021; 26: 1&#x2013;14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carmichael F, Charles S, Hulme C. Who will care? Employment participation and willingness to supply informal care. J Health Econ 2010; 29: 182&#x2013;190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20004991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sallnow L, Kumar S, Numpeli M. Home-based palliative care in Kerala, India: the Neighbourhood Network in Palliative Care. Prog Palliat Care 2010; 18: 14&#x2013;17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pfaff KA, Dolovich L, Howard M, et al.. Unpacking &#x2018;the cloud&#x2019;: a framework for implementing public health approaches to palliative care. Health Promot Int 2020; 35: 160&#x2013;170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30690474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aoun SM, Richmond R, Gunton K, et al.. The Compassionate Communities Connectors model for end-of-life care: implementation and evaluation. Palliat Care Soc Pract 2022; 16: 263235242211396.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9720808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36478890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Jong L, Stahmeyer JT, Eberhard S, et al.. Willingness and preparedness to provide care: interviews with individuals of different ages and with different caregiving experiences. BMC Geriatr 2021; 21: 207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7992803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33765937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Jong L, Schmidt T, Stahmeyer JT, et al.. Willingness to provide informal care to older adults in Germany: a discrete choice experiment. Eur J Health Econ 2022; 24: 425&#x2013;436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10060358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35689744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menzies RE, Menzies RG. How the fear of death shaped human society. Crows Nest: Allen &amp; Unwin, 2021, 448p.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kastenbaum R, Moreman CM. Death, society, and human experience. 12th ed. New York: Routledge, 2018, 1p.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barker JC. Neighbors, friends, and other nonkin caregivers of community-living dependent elders. J Gerontol B Psychol Sci Soc Sci 2002; 57: S158&#x2013;S167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11983742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quintiens B, Smets T, Chambaere K, et al.. Researching two Compassionate Cities: study protocol for a mixed-methods process and outcome evaluation. Palliat Care Soc Pract 2022; 16: 26323524221137601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9703481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36452070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quintiens B, Smets T, Chambaere K, et al.. Discomfort with suffering and dying, a cross-sectional survey of the general public. J Pain Symptom Manage 2023; 66: 529&#x2013;540.e6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37437645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matthys M, Chambaere K, Beernaert K, et al.. What does the general public know about palliative care? A population-based survey. BMJ Support Palliat Care. 2023: 386. DOI: 10.1136/ spcare-2023-004384.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37699664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma A, Minh Duc NT, Luu Lam Thang T, et al.. A Consensus-Based Checklist for Reporting of Survey Studies (CROSS). J Gen Intern Med 2021; 36: 3179&#x2013;3187.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8481359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33886027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Vlaamse Statistische Autoriteit. Structuur van de bevolking [Internet], https://statistieken.vlaanderen.be (2021, accessed 13 January 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baruch Y, Holtom BC. Survey response rate levels and trends in organizational research. Hum Relat 2008; 61: 1139&#x2013;1160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoddinott SN, Bass MJ. The dillman total design survey method. Can Fam Physician 1986; 32: 2366&#x2013;2368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2328022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21267217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noonan K, Horsfall D, Leonard R, et al.. Developing death literacy. Prog Palliat Care 2016; 24: 31&#x2013;35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kolb DA. Experiential learning: experience as the source of learning and development. 2nd ed. Upper Saddle River, NJ: Pearson Education Inc, 2015, 390p.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charalambous A. (ed.) Informal caregivers: from hidden heroes to integral part of care [Internet]. Cham: Springer International Publishing, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kozlov E, Carpenter BD, Rodebaugh TL. Development and validation of the Palliative Care Knowledge Scale (PaCKS). Palliat Support Care 2017; 15: 524&#x2013;534.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28025952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lester D. The factorial structure of the revised collett&#x2013;lester fear of death scale. Death Stud 2004; 28: 795&#x2013;798.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15446287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson WG, Williams JE, Bost JE, et al.. Exposure to death is associated with positive attitudes and higher knowledge about end-of-life care in graduating medical students. J Palliat Med 2008; 11: 1227&#x2013;1233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2941667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19021486</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boumans NPG, Dorant E. Double-duty caregivers: healthcare professionals juggling employment and informal caregiving. A survey on personal health and work experiences. J Adv Nurs 2014; 70: 1604&#x2013;1615.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24289650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onyx J, Bullen P. Measuring social capital in five communities. J Appl Behav Sci 2000; 36: 23&#x2013;42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Degroot AMB, Dannenburg L, Vanhell JG. Forward and backward word translation by bilinguals. J Mem Lang 1994; 33: 600&#x2013;629.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darren G. SPSS for windows step by step: a simple study guide and reference, 17.0 update. 10th ed. India: Pearson Education India, 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osborne JW, Costello AB. Sample size and subject to item ratio in principal components analysis. Pract Assess Res Eval 2004; 9: 11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Westreich D, Greenland S. The table 2 fallacy: presenting and interpreting confounder and modifier coefficients. Am J Epidemiol 2013; 177: 292&#x2013;298.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3626058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23371353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broese Van Groenou MI, De Boer A. Providing informal care in a changing society. Eur J Ageing 2016; 13: 271&#x2013;279.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4992501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27610055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rutherford AC, Bu F. Issues with the measurement of informal care in social surveys: evidence from the English Longitudinal Study of Ageing. Ageing Soc 2018; 38: 2541&#x2013;2559.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grindrod A, Rumbold B. Healthy End of Life Project (HELP): a progress report on implementing community guidance on public health palliative care initiatives in Australia. Ann Palliat Med 2018; 7(Suppl. 2): S73&#x2013;S83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29764174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rib&#xe9; JM, Salamero M, P&#xe9;rez-Testor C, et al.. Quality of life in family caregivers of schizophrenia patients in Spain: caregiver characteristics, caregiving burden, family functioning, and social and professional support. Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract 2018; 22: 25&#x2013;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28799427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Librada Flores SL, Molina EH, Osuna JB, et al.. All with you: a new method for developing compassionate communities &#x2013; experiences in Spain and Latin-America. Ann Palliat Med 2018; 7(Suppl. 2): S15&#x2013;S31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29764170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abel J, Kingston H, Scally A, et al.. Reducing emergency hospital admissions: a population health complex intervention of an enhanced model of primary care and compassionate communities. Br J Gen Pract 2018; 68: e803&#x2013;e810.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6193793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30297434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wozencroft AJ, Pate JR, Griffiths HK. Experiential learning and its impact on students&#x2019; attitudes toward youth with disabilities. J Exp Educ 2015; 38: 129&#x2013;143.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>